yes critically helps to manifest good or
ill health within a human being and of
course then you can go on to saying
healthy human being sitting in a healthy
human families sitting in healthy human
communities in healthy bio regional
alliances and in healthy ecosystems and
a healthy planet so what affects that
microbial ecosystem within us of course
is the environment and the bizarre thing
we also talked about that that we live
in a world where we have a food industry
that sells us food not caring about
health and we have health industry that
treats illness that has a pathogenic
approach to health rather than taking a
salute to genic approach in paying
attention to the importance of what we
eat and the environmental health around
us we're beginning to see the first
steps with Biophilia and biomimicry and
hospitals showing that it's very clearly
the people are clear that people heal
faster in hospitals where they have
access to green nature and can see trees
because we are biophilic creatures and
also we're beginning to have the first
voices that all this killing of the
microbial flora around us is actually
creating problems in the immune system
development of children and it's it's
wrong to have children in a sterile
environment because they can never
develop this diverse internal ecosystem
that maintains health throughout their
lives and this begins with feeding
mother's milk rather than then formula
milk if possible for some people it's
not possible but but for most people it
is and and it's so important to help the
child develop a healthy interior eCos
and so is that the child has contact
with dirt and with a wide variety of
microbes that can populate the ecosystem
within this includes the diversity of
lactobacillus initiatives and and and
yogurt and all those kind of things
kaffir but it also includes fungal
biodiversity and and bacterial
biodiversity and so a scale inking
saluto genic health generating approach
pays attention of how we can help the
manifestation of health the emergence of
health as a emergent property of a
complex dynamic system at the scale of
the individual and at the scale of the
ecosystem within which the individual
has their life because of course all
these environmental stresses are
massively influencing how health emerges
at the lower level and at the higher
level at the biosphere health so it was
just wonderful to finally talk to
somebody who's one of the world's most
renowned health specialists who was
working for the Australian Government as
the head of public health for a large
part of Sydney for a while and then went
back into academia and spent a few years
in Malaysia running the unit of the UN
University that does research to support
health policy and now he is back at in
Sydney building this platform for
planetary health at the University of
Sydney and we talked about possible
collaborations he invited me to
contribute to a book and exciting the
world so started dreaming into this idea
of maybe the world doesn't just need a
World Economic Forum it actually
needs a planetary health forum and how
that forum could look and how it might
be a decentralized forum so more people
could get involved with it and who might
be keep actors in participating in
funding such a vision of an annual
planetary health forum and for me it's
just such a wonderful deeply gratifying
development to know that in a tiny
little way and and only for some of the
people involved I have provided
frameworks of thinking the kind of
intellectual scaffolding that they have
used to develop the field of planetary
health further and I'm also really
excited to re-enter this new health
center to in more detail now read The
Lancet Rockefeller Commission report on
planetary health which you can just
download on the internet and to look at
how everything I do my work with guy
education could potentially take a turn
towards developing courses that look at
this scale linking saluto genic design
for human and Planetary health and
ultimately the word regeneration
captures in one word what I was working
on in my Teague PhD research in 2003
four five and six really I already
started to understand this link when I
was doing my master's in holistic
science and suggested that ecological
design was the practice and of the
holistic Sciences and the holistic
participatory integral worldview that we
were exploring at Yamaha college
and while in human terms 12 years seems
like a long time in terms of the
transition we're in I'm amazed that we
now find that this concept of planetary
health is catching on and that there's
real support in working on it and it and
the important bit is that it becomes
change oriented action-oriented
implemented as quickly as possible
and that means that we need to
collaborate with organizations like the
common land foundation like the
ecosystems restoration camp Foundation
and the different ecosystems restoration
comes that gianlu and the co-operative
has helped to launch is launching now in
different parts of the world and all the
good work of the people in this wider
movement that I've called regeneration
rising Kara Sanford's worked with
regenerative business and they her
influence on the wonderful work of
Gregory lambda and Ethan Rowland and
their different outfits the the region
network and their hard work on trying to
create an actionable process that brings
funding into ecosystems restoration and
at the same time finds a way of
measuring and verifying a regenerative
impact on healthy ecosystems function in
a particular place in order to make sure
that there is a certain check and
balance on where the funding goes and
that it actually has an impact on
salucci genic design of a particular
place
regeneration international linking up
lots of people around the planet that
work on regeneration the global
ecosystem the global eco village network
has come on board with the term
regeneration and sees their network of
communities as community focused field
study and experimental sites to bring
about a way that humans live in support
of the healthy ecosystem function of the
ecosystems they inhabit so in many ways
these communities aim to become saluto
genic health of generating communities
and there would be a lot of studying
that could be done there on the impact
of living in an eco village community on
psychological mental physical health the
person that I took the word salud to
Genesis from when I when I together with
Seton Baxter coined the term salud to
jannecke design is called era antonov
ski and era antonov ski in a book called
health stress and coping looked at how
Holocaust survivors were able to live to
a ripe old age and and somehow deal with
the trauma that they had lived through
in concentration camps and what he found
is that with after thousands of
interviews is that social cohesion and
being bound in a meaningful story that
made them connected to their roots their
future their present their community and
the world was a key element of being
able to live through and also to deal
with the trauma generated by these
horrific experiences afterwards and so
um
ecovillages have an enormous amount of
social cohesion and community cohesion
and in that they create a framework of
meaning for people that helps them heal
and makes them healthier people so as
you can see in this planetary health
perspective we walk through all the four
quadrants of the integral framework we
we look at both the interior individual
and the interior collective though the
worldview the value system the the
deeper insights of interconnection but
also the cultural process of bringing
forth a way of living together that is
creating a saluto genic culture and then
on the outside in the exterior
individual and the exterior collective
dimensions it is about creating health
as we look at product design
architecture Community Design industrial
ecology spire Ridge or city city and
urban design bio regional planning and
the wider than bioregion co-operative
networks that can happen at the national
and international scale and we see these
saluto genic networks emerging now they
are all these organizations that I've
mentioned already and they're many more
and we know that in order to address
climate change which is basically dyers
fever of planetary response to our
destructive and degenerative practices
over the last five thousand years and
particularly the last 250 300 years
since the Industrial Revolution really
got going and and we need this luta
genic response at all scales
and the good thing is it is already
happening there are people looking into
healthier materials that are biomaterial
based that don't off-gas and because
that's another key element of health
the air we breathe and whether it's
dealing with air pollution in cities and
and finally banning internal combustion
engines initially from cities and then
from entire bio regions and as soon as
possible from the planet and shifting
towards electric engines and hydrogen
engines possibly in some cases that do
not have those motions emissions that
have such a strong impact on human
health but it's also about stopping to
use all the byproducts of the chemical
industry which off-gas toxic chemicals
and therefore create very unhealthy
indoor environments many offices with
their cheap carpets and the glues used
in the furniture and the plastics used
in the furniture and the materials and
the curtains and then fire regulations
adding flame retardants for everything
which are demonstrated as being
carcinogenic and yet we we we still have
regulations that force us to put these
carcinogens on every hotel room pillow
and every hotel room bed sheet and many
public building upholsteries and so on
so you can see that there's something
about this concept of planetary health
as a scale linking factor that
demonstrates whether we are acting
regenerative Li or degenerative Li and
that there is so much work to be done
also as I mentioned before in
particularly the way we grow food and we
grow biomaterials and we how food
affects our health that I'm just
thrilled to have made this connection
and this was a rather long diary entry I
wonder if anybody actually gets to this
point and listens to it all the way to
the end but I would love your comments
any links that people have to health
related articles and groups that work on
this intersection between human health
environmental health and planetary
health I'd be very interested and I just
hope that I find a new way of creating
maybe an institute or some kind of
association that allows me to receive
funding to be able to do this work more
because one of the other things that I
talked with Anthony come upon about is
that I find it very hard to join this
meeting at the the famous Bellagio
Center on Lake Como and that the
Rockefeller Foundation has wonderful
place I'm sure and meeting there with
with would brilliant people to talk
about planetary health is something that
that I would learn a lot from but maybe
I could also contribute something too
but very often the people who meet are
financed by governments or by the
universities that they work for and
independent practitioner academic
futurists educators pathfinders thought
leaders whatever category you want to
force me into often don't
the wherewithal to attend these meetings
and so I do sometimes but every time I
go to one of those meetings and it's
five days and it takes true they days to
get there and come back I've basically
spent seven days of my holiday allowance
and I didn't need to work harder to feed
the family and have shortchanged my
daughter and my wife from time with me
and while of course some of that is
justifiable in the planetary emergency
and urgency that were facing as some
wise person recently said to me it's not
all about what kind of world we leave to
our children it's also maybe even more
importantly about what kind of children
we leave to the world and so my role as
a father and being there for my daughter
having taken the responsibility to bring
her onto this planet in a deep crisis of
planetary health and facing the
potential that she will live through
some of the roughest decades that
humanity has lived through for many many
millennia and still being hopeful that
maybe if we all together get things
right and we start the decade of
ecosystem restoration in 2020 or maybe
better tomorrow and we make it the kick
start of the century of regeneration
then after a few turbulent decades which
were already in the midst of